Heat. Heat. N.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello everybody. Good evening, good day
wherever you are. I hope you're all
doing great and welcome back to the Ask
a Bijit Show. Today we are doing episode
240.
So I'm going to be taking questions only
from the live chat today. Uh no
questions selected from the comments.
It's going to be all live all
interactive. And before we take the
questions let's see who all is there on
the live chat. I can see Mr. Unknown I
can say PM Tjas B Ain Raja Akash Kumar
Mr. Unknown again. Random skull.
Ah, Sadhart, Surrender, Gupta, Anand
Pay, Mangabonia, Mayangri, Tiwari,
Adridge,
Deesh, Kumar, Rahul, Dunak, Vidiar,
Sar Priti, Krishna Raunad from the
Surinamese Netherlands. Shri Ramchandra
Anamaha Shubam Bardaj Geopolitical Dubai
from Indor Dilling Peggu Raj Lalit Sabir
Kachu Kapalin Manu Krishna Mr. 88ers,
Kalik. So, Kofil Ludini Nayush um from
Bangladesh. Aryan Takur, Pranal from
Kolkata, really now Deosman Das Das
Gupta, Oscar Madison, two idiot NRIs,
Goofy Cat, Kish Gupta, May Manik Sarcar,
Adita Raj Singh, Ratur, Alks, Shri Anol.
Who else? Who else do we have? I can see
Ankit Mahapatra Abin of Mishra Shubankar
Nagi Mupti Sudaran Deva Sarin Dara
Samboy Chakraati Britam Sharma Prexen
Sparkling Note Lotus Raika Humbli Shivam
Shirokar and lots and lots of other
people. Feminist slayer Raj Indulkar
Rahul
Raawanchi Praar Gupta Anonymous Raini
Deep Rushi Rushi God Hershel Clash with
Pushkar Mommy of
Diu Savary Set Ragavir Solanki Ubar Men
Hoy Jagdish Mali Arpit Raju Rajput
Vamshi Khal and everybody else all right
greetings to all of you. Thank you so
much for being on the live chat on this
live stream. Thank you so much for your
viewership and let's get going with the
questions. Uh okay, what questions do we
have? Let's
see. Shri Ramachandra Namaha says, "What
is India doing to influence to increase
its influence in Africa?" Um it's an
interesting question. Africa is a
gigantic place. It's the largest
continent. If we disregard Eurasia as a
whole, what are we doing? I think u the
government may not be prioritizing
Africa the way Africa should be
prioritized but we have a lot of
peopleto-people ties going back
centuries maybe thousands of years
Indians have uh been living in eastern
Africa for I don't know how many
centuries mainly Indians from the
western western part of India mainly
mainly gujaratis uh and some other
Indians as well uh Tanzania Kenya etc
all these places uh Uh so there is that
of course and we
u we have some military kind of ties
with some countries. U we we obviously
have a very special place called
Mauritius. Okay let's go to the map
since we are discussing
Africa. Uh let us go to the map and
let's put it on the screen so that we
can have the right
context. So here's uh here is the map on
our screen. Oh no thank you. So
uh we have historical ties with uh the
eastern part of Africa especially
Tanzania, Kenya. Historically it would
even have been Somalia, Ethiopia all the
way to Egypt etc. But you know Tanzania,
Kenya
etc. Even Mosambique I suppose we have
lots of Indians living there. Uh when it
comes to Mauritius, we have a special
relationship because uh the majority of
the people of Mauritius are of Indian
origin. They are culturally and
ethnically still very Indian. Lots of
Indian origin people in reunion which is
a part of France and with Moraicius we
have u military kind of uh we we have u
there's a military dimension to the
relationship as well. Uh when it comes
to the island of Agalea, Agalega Agalea
uh yeah here we have it. Okay. Vans and
is north Agalea and south Agelga is not
that important from our perspective. So
we operate a military and air force base
etc in Agalea. As you can see it's a
reasonably well ordered established
place. I'm not showing you anything
that's classified. It's all public you
know open source information anyone can
see this and yeah so we our government
operates this this is ven we have agala
shiva mandonder over here and so on so
yeah this is an air base let's say and
uh military base you could say that is
jointly operated by India and maicius uh
we had something like that in with se
shells as well but did not quite work
out I think it was somewhere here It was
called Azumpsion. Yeah. Did not quite
work out because certain other nations,
certain other powers
interfered. Uh but yeah, so we have a
lot of ancient ties with the region. Our
government is taking some initiatives in
uh in connecting us with Africa. I'm
sure we can do a lot more is what I
would actually say. And Africa is
important from a variety of
perspectives. I know it's not the
richest continent, it's the poorest
continent. We know that and uh but it's
it's important from various perspectives
like if you have good ties with the
African countries then you know the you
can expect their support in the United
Nations when it comes to voting and so
on. All these things matter in the
world. So I think India should actually
uh take Africa a lot more seriously than
than we currently are taking it. Uh yeah
so that's what I can tell you.
Uh ah says if someone tells you he has
time traveled from the future to the
present from the future to the present
okay uh how will you verify if he is
speaking the truth there's no actual
real way of verifying if the person is
speaking the truth but if the person is
you can ask some questions you know if
if the person has been able to travel
through try time it means that he or she
is coming from uh a period of time where
Our understanding of physics and applied
physics is extraordinarily more advanced
than what it is today. Because if you're
able to, you know, uh manage that travel
through time, it means your
understanding of physics and your in
your uh control of physics is
incredible. So you could ask questions
about let's say some some open problems
that haven't been solved today. You
know, how do you reconcile quantum
mechanics in gravity for example? That's
one question you could ask them. Or what
is the physics of time travel? We
understand it theoretically Einstein
Rosen bridges bridges and stuff but how
did you manage it and what's the basic
principles behind it? That's some
questions you could ask and uh you could
I suppose there is no guaranteed way of
knowing whether the person is telling
the truth. But you could ask them to
predict something for example that's
going to happen in the next uh 2 weeks
or 3 months you know a reasonably short
period of time. make some predictions
and let's see if those come true and so
on. So you could uh have some kind of a
questionnaire uh for a person who claims
to have traveled from the past and based
on that perhaps you could get some
indication of whether they are telling
the truth or
not. Okay.
Um let's see more
questions. Uh geopolitical dub says will
China bow to the sole superpower?
China does not intend to bow to the
United
States. Uh Xiinping has this great
dream, the dream of the great
rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.
Excuse me. And the dream is that China
will become an equal of the United
States by around
2050. Now, right now, China is not an
equal of the US by no means. Uh but
technologically, they are catching up.
And
uh so if if the great dream is for China
to be an equal of the US and eventually
surpass the US, replace and displace the
US as the great as the only great power
in the world, then you will not uh bow
to the great super the sole superpower.
So China is not bowing to the superpower
right now. There's this complete uh
allout trade war, tariff war that's
that's brewing right now between China
and the United States. And the US has
unleashed this trade war, tariff war. Uh
President Donald Trump has unleashed it.
And China is not u you know taking a
step back. They have unleashed or
retaliatory tariffs on the US. If the US
has placed 140% of whatever the tariffs
are, the Chinese have responded by
putting 125% tariffs on the US most
items, which means that the two nations
are essentially decoupling and the trade
between them is essentially frozen or
dead. So witness we are witnessing a
bifurcation a decoupling of the world
order. On the one hand you will have
nations like the US and all its allies
all it's its flock so to say. On the
other hand you will have nations like
China and Russia and Iran and North
Korea and whoever else would like wants
to be part of that alliance or access or
whatever you want to call it.
So, China is positioning itself as a
leader of that group. Uh, and China is
not going to bow to the sole superpower.
So, uh, look, the US wants to curtail
China's rise. They want to curtail
China's growth. And they have lots of
justifications for why they have
unleashed this tariff war against China.
Lots of justifications. Some of them are
true. Some of them, you could say, uh,
whatever.
uh but um so they have these
justifications and they don't want China
to rise further. So how does a nation
rise? Through its economy if your
economy grows you have more money to
spend on other things like military and
so on. So they don't want the economy of
China to grow so much and by cutting off
China's access to the US market, to
European markets, other markets. uh they
want to curtail China's rise and they
also want to deny China sensitive
technologies like you know Nvidia chips
the high-end Nvidia chips and various
various other technologies well the
Chinese have already acquired whatever
they wanted to acquire you know and they
are not so far behind when it comes to
cutting edge chip manufacturing they
have apparently developed their own
photo lithography machines and they are
not very far behind so it's kind of it's
kind of a case of of uh closing in the
barn doors after the horses have bolted
or something like that. Um, and the real
fear is that the Chinese are
technologically almost at the same level
as the US now. They have really caught
up and they've really really put in the
hard yards. They've really invested
trillions of dollars in into their
education system and into their
technological high-tech sector and all
of that is paying fruit now. So even
though China may not have the kind of
military might that the US has today,
the Chinese don't have hundreds of extr
territorial military bases and so on.
They don't have any of that. They don't
have the power projection capabilities
of the US. They don't have the nuclear
arsenal that the US has. They have a
fraction of that. But technologically
they are almost neck-to- neck with the
US. And the great arms race that we are
living in right now is the AI arms race,
artificial intelligence. Now most of us
don't see we we must be wonder most
people will be wondering what what's the
big deal about AI artificial
intelligence but well it's not supposed
to be seen and visible it'll slowly take
away your jobs and all that that's a
different story uh but the AI race is
going to be the most consequential race
uh of our time maybe in the entire
history of humanity and whoever cracks
that that breaches that level the ASI
level is going to be the winner and uh
you know so that's the arms race and the
Chinese are definitely up there with the
US. Uh the US has various uh public AI
systems like uh Anthropic and uh Open AI
and uh whatever else, Google's Gemini
and so on. The Chinese have their
DeepSeek R1 and and Manus and whatnot.
But there's a deeper arms race that's
going on behind the scenes, behind
closed doors, a secret arms race where
the real AI systems are being
unleashed privately by the militaries
and the governments. And that's the real
arms race. And those military AI
capabilities will be like a thousand
times what what you can see in your chat
GPD or whatever like way orders of
magnitude greater. And that's the arms
race and that's what the Americans fear.
So they want to deny China the cutting
edge GPUs, Nvidia chips and whatever
else they can deny the Chinese and they
want to constrain the economy. But the
Chinese are going to u they're not going
to give up. This is going to be a fight
to the finish essentially. So China will
not bow to the superpower. I assure you
of
that. Ramach Krishna Paranh says why is
India not doing anything to control
control and deport the Bangladeshes and
Rohingya's illegal immigrants? There are
reports claiming West Bengal government
providing land etc etc etc reports
allegedly. Well
look why is the government of India not
doing this? I don't think I'm the right
person to answer that question. I think
the only entity that can answer that
question is the government of
India. You know in 2014 I don't know
which minister had reported this. It's
on the record. In 2014, it was reported
officially that there were about roughly
5 crore illegal immigrants in India,
which is 50 million. That's larger than
the population of most countries. That's
2014. Today is
2025. I would guess the population would
have doubled. Doubled. So let's say we
have hypothetically a 100 million
illegal immigrants in India. Can you
imagine the strain on our
resources and and the hardship that our
people face just because of this
additional 100 million people? So it's
it's it's an enormous problem and it's
something that we are just disregarding
and sweeping under the carpet. And these
immigrants they will multiply, they will
procreate, they will have children who
will be who will grow up in India, who
will be born in India, grow up in India
and they will consider themselves
Indian. And the longer we wait to solve
the problem, the the the deeper it gets
entrenched. It's something we've seen in
Manipur. It's something we have seen or
we are seeing all across India.
Rohingya's brought in from god knows
what places in the 2010s or whenever
even perhaps been even before that and
settled in every part of India. Why is
the government not doing anything about
this? I am not quite sure why. Uh beats
me but I think the government should do
something about this. I mean it's a
national security
threat. It's a major national security
threat and no self-respecting nation
should uh allow this to happen. And it
it raises questions about whether we are
genuinely sovereign. You know a
sovereign nation would not tolerate
this. Are we really sovereign? Is it all
just slogan slogan slogan in India? I
don't know about that. So I don't have
answers to your question. I myself am
seeking the answer. Why is the
government not doing anything about
this? Right.
Kapalin says, "Is the sun white? The
sun, our star, is it white?" I mean, if
you study physics, if you open a physics
textbook, I think from I think from I
don't know uh from the primary school
level, I think if you have a good
textbook, you'll be taught that the sun
is a white star. It emits white light.
And that goes completely against
everything we understand of of the
world, right? I mean we have been seeing
sunlight since the time we were born all
of us. And what do we think of sunlight?
Golden color right? In the morning it's
nice and golden soft and golden. In the
afternoon it's harsh and golden and
yellow yellowish light yellowish. In in
the evening it's again that golden hour
and then it becomes reddish as the sun
starts sinking under the horizon and
then it disappears. That's always shades
of yellow and and and red and orange.
Yellow, red, orange, mainly yellow,
right? That's how we see
sunlight. So, are these physics
textbooks lying is the question. Well,
the truth is, my dear friends, that the
sun is a white star. It emits perfectly
white light. But we see it as
yellow and and shades of whatever else,
orange and red. Why is that? It's
because of our atmosphere. Our
atmosphere filters the light. There is
something called rale scattering. R A L
E I G H. Raleigh scattering. Look it up.
It's a phenomenon in in well optical
physics, let's say, atmospheric physics.
It it's a physics phenomenon. Okay? And
in which wavelengths of light are
scattered in different ways. So, if you
look at the sky, let me show you
something quite I'm not sure if it's
going to work, if I'm going to be right
or not, but let's look at the color
wheel and let's see if yellow and blue
are on the opposite ends of the color
wheel. Let's do it together. I I have a
hunch, I've not done this before, that
yellow and red are on the opposite ends
of the color wheel. So, let's go to
color wheel. Yellow and blue images.
Okay, yellow and blue are kind of kind
of on opposite ends of the color wheel.
Kind of not exactly. Blue and orange are
on opposite ends of the color
wheel. So what happens is that uh the
the to to make it very simple without
going into the actual physics what
happens is that the atmosphere we we
have this planet and the planet has an
atmosphere that's why we have wind and
all that. So we can breathe. The
atmosphere absorbs certain wavelengths
of light and scatters certain
wavelengths of light. So
uh it absorbs blue. That's why the sky
looks blue. It's not actually blue but
the atmosphere retains that blue in it.
Okay. The very simple way of explaining
it. It absorbs the blue and scatters the
yellow. That's why the white suddenly
looks like it has been turned it has
been split into two colors. The blue
stays in the sky and the sunlight that
we see appears yellow. Even water
appears to be bluish. Right? Uh so so
that's what happens because of
scattering of light through a process
called rale scattering. All right? But
the sun actually if you go out of the
atmosphere go into earth orbit you will
see that the sun is emitting white light
just pure white light but the atmosphere
and the processes that happen in the
atmosphere make it look like it is like
the light is
yellow. Right. Good question. Now, let's
take some other
questions. Um, what did I just see?
Okay, Sora Kumar says, "Could there be a
link between the South American deity
Vira Kocha, uh, believed to have come
from across the oceans to civilize
ancient peoples and the figure of
Virochana, Bali's
analitor, Viracha was an Inca Emperor.
The Inca Empire in the 16th century was
at the time the world's largest
empire. Um let's uh let us go through uh
the map and try and figure out where all
this
is.
Okay. So, we're going to go to uh the
Americas and it was here Peru, Bolivia,
this entire region.
um and also Ecuador etc. that you had
that's where you had the Inca Empire and
there were great emperors and it was the
largest empire of its time around the
16th century until the point where the
Spaniard the Spanish concistadors
destroyed it and one of the Inca
emperors his name was
Viracha Viracha
um I think he was the father of
Pakuti strange name right Viracha Pakuti
I think Vira Kocha
was the father of patchakouti. Let's
let's Google it together. Uh because I
don't quite remember the exact um yeah
so let's do this.
Vraa and
[Music]
Pakuti
Viracha
Pakuti. So this guy Pakuti was the was
the great essentially the founder of the
great empire. Who was his predecessor?
Yeah Vira Kocha. There we have it.
Virucha was the father of
Pakuti. That's right. So this is a king
of the Inca Empire. But I think there is
a mythical figure as well as well called
Vira Kucha. And the question lots of
Indians ask or or wonder about is that
is was there some kind of connection
between Viraa and Vrochina because the
names sound kindly vaguely kind of
vaguely uh similar. Well, as far as I
know, I have seen no evidence of uh
there being a connection, which doesn't
mean there is no connection. The absence
of evidence is not the evidence of
absence. Like I have said a few years
ago, the point is I don't know of any
clinching evidence or even
circumstantial evidence that connects
the two beyond the vague similarity of
the two names. Okay? Uh but there have
been people who have written about this.
For example, let's Google this
gentleman. Okay.
Um uh let us Google a name together.
Let's go to Google and let's write Bikhu
Chaman
Lal. Bikhu Chaman Lal. So this gentleman
Bhu Chaman Lal he wrote a book called
Hindu America. Now a I personally have
never had the time to read this book to
peruse this book. I hear it's a
fascinating book and uh he wrote this I
don't know about a century or so ago if
I'm if I'm not mistaken
uh when was it written let me see does
it have a date okay
1941 and apparently he looks like he was
a great fan of Mr. Gandhi which is okay
and so on. Uh but the question is what
does he write in the book? So Hindu
imprints on America, children of the
sun, Indra and Ganesha in America, Hindu
legends in America, the glorious Mayers,
the great Aztecs from India to America,
Buddhism in America, when India ruled
the waves and so on. So if you are
interested, I would say that maybe you
could check out this book, Hindu America
by Viku Manl. It's available online.
It's available I think for download. um
for
free. So check it out. I personally
haven't read it, but it I hear it's a
it's a rather intriguing book. I'm not
sure how much of the evidence is
presented or whether the evidence is is
is rigorous or not quite rigorous, but
it's an interesting book. That's what I
hear. So check it out. But uh as far as
this question is concerned, I personally
have uh no evidence that connects the
two. I'm not aware of any uh hard
evidence clinching evidence that
connects Vira Kocha with Virro
Chana.
Okay. Vikramadur says, "You often
highlight American strength, US
strength, but as a historian, don't
empires fall. Why not consider India and
bricks as future poles? Isn't US
dominance also subject to decline over
time? All empires fall? Every single
empire that we know of in history has
fallen. No question about
it. The last great empire that fell was
the British Empire. But did it really
fall? It didn't quite fall. It simply
trans it it transformed into something
else. It transformed into the US Empire.
And the US empire, I would say, is at
its pinnacle. It's never been as
powerful as it is today. So empires
absolutely do fall. There's no question
about it. It doesn't mean it's going to
fall next week. Just because all empires
fall doesn't mean that now the US empire
will fall next
week. There are
cycles. History is cyclical like they
say. So if you look at u the average u
duration of an empire it's roughly 250
or 300 years. 250 to 300 years. If you
look at Indian history we've had various
imperial cycles ourselves. If you look
at Chinese history, there have been
imperial cycles and so on. So if you
look at the Morian Empire, it was about
what 250 300 years. If you look at the
Kushan Empire, it was again 250 or 300
years. The the Gupta Empire was about
200 250 years and so on. That's how it
goes generally. Now some empires last
longer. The Roman Empire, Eastern Roman
Empire lasted much much longer uh than
the Western Roman Empire and and so on.
So it depends on so many factors. You
can't do a simplistic game theoretical
calculation of of how long an empire
will last. I'm not sure even if you can
set up a game like that because games
are usually competitive or whatever
games. But my my point is um empires do
fall but there's no indication that the
the US empire is uh is showing signs of
falling. It's actually showing signs of
rising. There are issues uh when it
comes to
uh morality and ethics and all that
which every empire has. There are issues
of societal decay and decline. Uh that
is visible kind of but the military
strength and overall hard power is
incredible. It's never been higher. Uh
why not consider India and BRICS as
future polls? Well, one can certainly
consider even Sri Lanka as a potential
future poll 100 years down the line.
India
obviously is a much more powerful and
much more viable potential future pool.
Sure. But if you look at India's
structural the way India is
structured and the kind of strengths and
weaknesses India has, India doesn't show
signs or symptoms of of becoming a
future power. India doesn't show that.
India has too many systematic systemic
and structural inefficiencies,
deficiencies and
problems.
Uh one example is that India simply is
not agile enough. India doesn't make
decisions fast enough and implement
those decisions fast enough. You pass a
law then you you to go through 78
different Supreme Court cases and then
you take back some of the laws and you
to maybe roll it back and then again try
it after 3 years and then maybe there's
incremental progress but a lot has
changed. Come on, is this the way you
rule an empire? So, you know, too much
inefficiency in India which has
historically since
1947 relegated India to to and also ran
status and
bricks I do not consider bricks to be a
future
pole. An empire has only one center of
power. You can't have an empire by
coalition. Yes, you the the the Aztecs
had a tripartite, you know, trilateral
confederation kind of thing, but they
also had just one pole in the center and
the other twos were the other two
wereas. There are many examples like
that. So, if bricks becomes a a genuine
pole in the future, it's going to be
ruled by just one entity either China or
or Russia. The others will
be right. So you can consider anybody as
a future poll. But is it genuinely
capable of being a future pole? Does
India have the hard-headedness and
ruthlessness of the US? I mean does does
India have that? Does India have any
leader that that can take India in that
direction? Someone like Chandra Gupta
Moria, someone like Chanaka, someone
like Rajendra Chola or or somebody like
like Samodra Gupta? We don't have any of
those leaders today. the system is such
that it doesn't produce leaders of that
caliber or
quality. So um that's why India is not
taken seriously as as a future
superpower. Uh I I hope that assessment
is wrong and something will change but
you will need a drastic drastic drastic
incredibly drastic change a
mind-boggling change in India for
something like that to happen. The
entire system will have to be
overturned.
No more constitution, no more democracy.
Only then you become a superpower. Um so
yes in the US dominance is subject to
decline over time. Yes. So maybe the US
will last another 150 years only only
150 years more and maybe then some other
power will come up or maybe it will last
another 50 years. We don't know. We
haven't seen the future.
Maybe the Chinese will de develop ASI
before the Americans and then they will
rule the world for a thousand years and
the Americans will be left behind. So
that could happen in the next two weeks
also. You never know. But from whatever
science, indications and data points are
available in the public domain. I don't
see uh any sign of US of the US empire
falling anytime soon. Things may be
happening behind closed doors that we
are not aware of. That could change the
entire scenario in 2 weeks. But from
what was visible in
public, the US is here to stay for a
long time. And India doesn't even take
this is doesn't even it's not playing
the game seriously. It's not playing the
game to
win. Maybe in a 100 years India may be a
superpower. It's possible everybody
wants to be wishpower but no one wants
to do the hard work. So yeah.
Well, anonymous scientist says a recent
house white house statement claimed that
they are capable of manipulating space
and time. What do they what do they mean
by this? I think it was I think I saw it
somewhere on X yesterday or something a
statement an unofficial statement by one
of the officials I don't remember who it
was in which there's this one sentence
that says that we are capable of
manipulating space and time.
So, should we take that literally that
they have technology that can meddle
with the space-time continuum? Does it
mean they're capable of time travel?
Does it mean that they're capable of
creating wormholes and traversible
wormholes? What does what does it mean
by by that? Or maybe they just mean that
we have I don't maybe it's a maybe the
the speaker was taking poetic
license. Maybe he was saying that we
have the fastest missiles in the world,
hypersonics. So it's almost like we are
uh manipulating space and time. I'm not
sure what what the what what that
statement meant. You can either take it
completely literally which would be
mind-boggling or maybe the person was
taking poetic license. Two scenarios I
can present to you. I don't know which
one is correct.
So,
okay. Nefron says, "Is that Japanese
history is more oldest than Okay. Is
Japanese history older than Indian
history?" Well, uh,
look, Japan's,
uh, imperial history goes back about 2
and a half or 3,000 years roughly. Uh,
maybe slightly more than 3,000 years.
uh and they have these
um foundation myths, you know, creation
myths.
Uh I forget the name of the two
individuals, Inagami, Inagami, something
like that. So, it goes back about 3,000
or maybe 3 and a half thousand years or
so. Uh that's that's about how old
Japanese history is. And obviously if
you do archaeological research and all
you'll find science of human habitation
and reasonably well organized human
habitation that will go back more than
th,000 years for sure in Japan. No
question about it. You'll find that. Now
what about Indian
history? Well, we have signs of
habitation in India that go back I don't
know how many thousands of years and u
the oldest archaeological site that we
know of that goes back to the Sarasodi
Synindu times is Birana which is about 9
and a half thousand years. uh and and it
was constantly inhabited from 9 and a
half thousand years at least onwards. So
clearly Indian history is older and uh
there's so much more that need that that
remains to be excavated and and
researched from the archaeological
perspective. So when it comes to Asia,
it's pretty clear that India is the
oldest continuously existing
civilization, the oldest civilization
that we know of and definitely the
oldest culture and civilization in in
Asia. Perhaps the world per perhaps the
world. I'm sure that there were
civilizations that were older maybe
20,000 30,000 years old civilizations
which may have existed but we haven't
found evidence of that. So the
possibility exists but we haven't found
the evidence of that.
Uh so that's what I can tell you. You
can do your own research. Whatever I
said you can corroborate for yourself.
How old is Birana from carbon dating
dating perspective? How long was from
what time period onwards was birana
continuously inhabited? Uh what is the
oldest um depiction of a super supernova
in the archaeological records about
6,000 years ago and so on. All that is
India. So clearly um our history is the
oldest when it comes to at least Asia if
not the whole
world.
Um Aman Pit Singh says why do
geopolitical experts from your circle my
circle? Who's my circle? Okay. Why do
geopolitical experts from your circle
offer differing views on geopolitics? Uh
despite having the same ideology is it
makes it extremely difficult from the
viewers's perspective about whom to
believe. Well, that is a problem the
viewer will always have. Now, look, I
don't know who my circle is. I don't
think I'm part of a circle as far as I
know. I am uh yeah, I don't work with
other analysts or or or observers or or
whatever. Okay.
Um now let's let's understand one thing
when it comes to geopolitical analysis
geostrategic analysis you don't base
your analysis on
ideology. If you have an analyst who is
basing his or her uh observations and
analysis on ideology that person cannot
be taken
seriously. Your analysis has to be based
only on actual hard facts on what's
happening in the world from confirmed
sources and then an analytical model
which may be something you've learned
from somebody
somewhere. Maybe you've learned that
model from somewhere from a from
historical perspectives or maybe you
have a geoeconomic model or whatever.
But you need to have your own analytical
model through which you analyze what's
happening and then you form conclusions.
So it has to be a logical process. Maybe
you should employ what they call the
scientific method in
this. And uh there are people who do
that and there are people who don't do
that. Uh there are people who are
intuitive geopolitical analysts and they
go by gut feel. Then there are people
who do it on the basis of rigorous study
and
research. Uh so everybody is going to
interpret events and what's happening in
the world differently and that's why
they will offer different views. So that
is to be expected not no two opinions
will be exactly the same.
But if somebody is basing their their uh
views on ideology instead of actual hard
facts and logic then that person cannot
be taken seriously because that's not
how we do geopolitical anal analysis.
Now from the viewer's perspective who to
the question the conundrum is who do you
believe and who do you not take
seriously? That's always going to be a
question for the viewer. So to
understand to to figure out for yourself
as a viewer whom to believe and whom not
to believe you first of all need to
educate yourself a little bit about
geopolitics as to how geopolitical
analysis is
done and then you have to try and figure
out that this person so and so Mr. X or
Miss
Y whatever analysis they are doing what
is the mental framework analytical
framework they
use to to come to their
conclusions in some cases maybe that
analytical network um framework isn't
spelt out maybe it's not transparent in
which case you will not be able to
figure out what they're doing and how
they're coming to the conclusions And
there are lots of people like that. Um,
for example, in my case, I I base my
analysis on on hard data, u on hard
power. That's that's one of the
components of of the framework. Uh, what
is each nation's hard power score? Now,
I haven't put it out in the public
domain yet, but I have my own rankings
of every nation in terms of hard power.
And the US scores 91 or something. Uh,
Russia is Russia is 50 something, 53 or
something. China is 17 or 18 and India
is 4.9 and France is 4.2 or something.
So that's the top five in terms of just
hard power based on public source data
GDP and military spending and population
and and area and and power projection
and nuclear strength and uh energy
self-sufficiency and various other
factors. you take all those factors and
you have to create a an equation, a
formula that that spits out a hard power
score for each nation. So that kind of
tells you exactly where each nation
stands in relation to the other. So
that's one component of my analy analyt
analytical framework. And then I also
look at uh history. I mean you cannot
understand a nation and its the
conflicts it is uh embroiled in and what
its interests are without understanding
the nation's history and understanding
the nation's geography, understanding
its economic uh condition and so many
other things. So you have to take all of
these things into perspective in order
to have an informed view of what's
happening and you need that that is part
of what you call an analytical
framework and if an analyst doesn't have
that or if they're just doing just
winging it then you can't take it
seriously.
Um yeah so if you can figure out that
you have let's say you have five
geopolitical observers analysts who you
watch and if you can figure out for each
of those what their frameworks are then
you can judge for yourself which is
better or which is
not and it should not be a popularity
contest that the person who is the most
handsome the person who speaks the best
the person who who has the most jo in
talking I'm going to watch that person
he can't do it like that okay so
Yeah. All
right.
Mhm. Savaria S says, "Is Cuba irrelevant
in geopolitics?" That's a rather good
question, rather pertinent question.
Which nations are relevant and which
nations are not quite relevant in
geopolitics? And that's a that's a
question you have to ask yourself. And
uh you know you can't base the answer to
that question on um you know on on
sentimental things and all that you need
to have a really good huristic as to uh
which nations matter and on what are you
going to base whether whether a nation
matters or not. So there is a question
that you have to ask yourself when it
comes to geopolitical events. Which
events are consequential? Which events
are impactful and which events are not
so impactful? And that kind of gives you
a heristic as to which nations are
relevant. For example, look what's the
geopolitical impact of of something. So
you could you
know you could create a geopolitical
impact score for an event. Every event
that happens in the world has some kind
of geopolitical impact. Some of it is
localized, some of it is global. So
let's say we create a geopolitical
impact score of any event and the score
is from 1 to 10. One is the lowest
impact, 10 is the highest impact. So
what kind of event would you give a
geopolitical impact score of
10? I would say a nuclear war has impact
10 out of 10. An alien invasion has
impact 10 out of 10. or uh a
hypothetical global pandemic which kills
half of a population like the black
death in in medieval Europe that has a
geopolitical impact which is 10 out of
10 most impactful. What is something
that is very minor you know
minimal wider implications which is the
lowest geopolitical impact impact one
out of 10. It is like local election
results, your municipal election results
or some minor policy announcement in
your country or
or some student protests in some college
or university that has an impact of one
out of 10 the minimal possible impact.
So that's kind of how you you would
create a heristic score for geopolitical
impact. And then you have to ask
yourself if something happens in Cuba
where does it fall on the scale of 1 to
10. So let's say uh the president of
Cuba makes a policy announcement a new
policy is going to be implemented in the
country. Uh what's the impact score?
It's going to be closer to one than to
10,
right? Or if there's an election and
some new person is elected in Cuba,
what's going to be the global
repercussions repercussions of that?
it's going to be almost minimal almost
nothing. So once again the impact
geopolitical impact will be closer to
one than to 10. So from that perspective
if you look at Cuba it is kind of
unfortunately irrelevant in geopolitics.
Just being very realistic pragmatic
practical here nothing sentimental about
it. You have to analyze geopolitics in
this matter. So Cuba
unfortunately maybe for good for worse
it's not quite relevant in geopolitics.
Amisha says, "Can humans ever leave the
Milky Way
galaxy?"
Well, you know, before you
learn before you learn to
run, you to learn to walk. Before you
learn to walk, you learn to stand. So,
you first as a baby learn how to stand.
Then you learn how to start toddling on
two two feet. Then after a while you're
a little confident and then you start
you know running a little bit. So you
you you progress from standing to
walking to jogging to running and
sprinting and then you can start flying
and then you can going start going
supersonic then hypersonic then you can
have escape velocity which means you can
go into earth
orbit and that's where we are and maybe
you can break out of earth orbit and go
to go to the moon. We've kind of done
that and soon enough we'll break out of
Earth orbit and go to Mars. So that's
the limit of what we can achieve today.
And that's why Amisha asks this
question. Can humans ever leave the
Milky Way
galaxy? Um look, there is no law of
physics that says that we can't. So it's
perfectly fine within the laws of
physics. It doesn't break the laws of
physics. So we can theoretically leave
the Milky Way galaxy. But now what does
it take to do
that? Um first of all we'll need to
develop the kind of technology that will
allow us to break free of uh of the
sun's
gravity. So there is a certain escape
velocity for the sun as well for the
solar gravitational potential. We'll
have to break free of that and then
we'll have to go to the nearest star
first. The nearest star system is the
alpha proxima centtory system. That's
about 4 point something light years from
here. And uh if we travel at at the
speed of the fastest rocket chemical
rock that rocket that we have it would
take I don't know tens of thousands of
years most
likely. But there are certain
technologies that are almost available
to us. uh light sail technology for
example those techn such a technology
could enable us theoretically to travel
at about 30% of the speed of light which
means that we could reach Proxima
Centuri in 30 40 or so years
um it's possible we are almost there
that technology may be about a decade
away
uh you can use a very highowered lasers
to shine light on light sailed light
sail equipped spacecraft as light as
possible those spacecraft should be and
radiation pressure will will impel those
spacecraft forward in the direction of
Proxima Centtory and it could quickly uh
accelerate them to about 30% or so of
light speed in which case you could
reach the star system in about 30 or 40
years.
uh but initially we're going to have to
send nano spacecraft to Proxima Centuri
and then once we get the signal from
there and what not then maybe in the
next 30 40 50 years we can uh perhaps
think of sending humans. So that's just
the next star system four roughly four
light years away. Our galaxy the Milky
Way is about a 100,000 or so light years
in diameter. is a gigantic thing and
it's just a tiny speck of dust in the
global in the in the in the sphere of in
in the scale of things of the universe,
you know.
Um, so in order to leave the Milky Way
galaxy, we would have to break free of
the gravitational pull of the super
massive black hole at the center of the
galaxy. And I'm not sure what the escape
velocity of that is, but I'm sure we can
quickly calculate it if you want to. Um,
but what technology would we need for
that? because that would take um that
that process of leaving the galaxy and
going to let's say the nearest
neighboring galaxy large galaxy
Andromeda that process may take a
million years because that's the kind of
distance we're talking about you know so
u in a million years humans would have
evolved into something else so my point
is it is all possible it is
all
perfectly acceptable It isn't within the
realm of the laws of physics. It doesn't
break anything. But the only realistic
way of traveling outside of the galaxy
of of our galaxy and let's say going to
a neighboring galaxy, the only realistic
way of doing that in one human lifetime
would probably involve creating a
traversible
wormhole. that two the kind of
wormhole which you know where it exists
where the other end is which uh is
theoretically kind of okay uh there are
solutions of the Einstein equations of
general relativity that do allow for
this it's called an Einstein Rosen
bridge a wormhole but those wormholes
they want to their neck wants to snap
shut and the only way you can keep the
keep the neck of the wormhole open is by
having something really exotic in there
something like negative negative
mass negative mass or maybe a cosmic
string which is a defect topological
defect in the fabric of space time
itself which is a completely
hypothetical theoretical thing. We've
never observed that but it may exist. So
yeah it's it's far out there. It's all
in the realm of science fiction. It
doesn't quite break the laws of physics
but we have never seen those objects or
technologies ever. So it may be possible
but right now it's it's in the realm of
science fiction completely. But who
knows with the advent of artificial
super intelligence we may be able to
create traversible wormholes in the next
5 years. Who knows? Who knows? We'll
see.
Okay.
Um let's
um Shrea Shetty says, "Why does the logo
on KT Paris space suit bear no
resemblance to a rocket yet when viewed
upside down strongly resembles a goat
head?" Goat's head or is it Satan's?
Well, I haven't I I'm I'm not aware of
that. Katy Perry is the singer. Yeah, I
know of her. She went into space for 10
minutes. I know about that as well that
she had quite a bumpy splashdown on
Earth. I saw that as well, but I didn't
see what what she was wearing and what
logo was that. I have no idea. So, I
can't speculate. Sorry.
Um, Unar Kulkarnney says, "Is it really
the time for India to join hands with
China and trust it again after facing
many
betrayals?" There is no trust in
geopolitics, my
friends. And there are no betrayals in
geopolitics. You can only be betrayed if
you are stupid, foolish and
gullible. And India has kind of been
like that. stupid, foolish, gullible,
naive foreign policy for the most of the
time after 1947. That's what we've had.
So Indians feel that oh we have been
betrayed by China. China
acted the way any logical rational power
would behave.
Okay, nature abhors a vacuum and in
geopolitics power abhors a vacuum and
power is a force that pushes outwards.
So if you have two nations border to
border and one has more power than the
other that that power will push outwards
and it will grab territory. That's just
like a law of
nature. Okay. So if we became weak and
if we did not pay attention to Tibet, if
we did not pay attention to Oxai Chin,
we were busy doing god knows what and we
did not even know the Chinese were
constructing highways, it's not China's
fault. It's our fault that we were not
geopolitically ambitious enough to
safeguard Tibet, Tibet's independence
and so on. So I don't blame China. I
don't consider them to have backstabbed
us or betrayed us.
You should question your leaders for
betraying you. It is
they it is their their actions, their
neglect, their policies that led to
India losing territory and losing a war.
Even that war could have been won if we
had not neglected the armed forces and
the air force and so on. It's not
China's fault. I don't blame China one
bit there. the the Chinese leadership
was looking out for the Chinese national
interest. Why couldn't our leadership
look out for the Indian national
interest? That's my
question. Now, when it comes to China, I
trust
China to prioritize its national
interest. So, if you want to deal with
China, you should know exactly what
China's perception of its national
interest
is. And if you know what China's
perception of its national interest is,
you will know
what their red lines are and you will
know what their priorities
are and then if you can find ways of
working with them such that their some
of their priorities match your
priorities then you'll work with them
and it'll be a constructive relationship
and that's how you do it but you never
trust somebody you never trust anyone
ever you always keep double-checking
everything they do that's how it works
in
geopolitics there are no friends in
geopolitic politics. There are no
enemies in geopolitics. There is no
trust in geopolitics. There's no
betrayal in
geopolitics. So please understand these
things. These are the basics. These are
the ABCs of geopolitics. Um the problem
with India in the education system is
that we are not taught any of these
things. So we grow up completely
naive. But you will see the same
principles at play in domestic
politics. And Indians are great at
domestic politics. But they simply don't
realize that the same principles apply
at the global level as well in a
different kind of context. But the same
things apply in domestic politics in
your municipal politics or state level
politics. You will see the same
betrayals, the same backstabbing, the
same lack of amoral uh relationships,
the same lack of friendships, lack of
trust, same thing all over again. You'll
see. Of course, there will be some
cultural context to it which will kind
of cloud your eyes, but you know that's
how it works. So my point is India
should be open to working with everybody
and India should ensure that it doesn't
give anybody the opportunity to to take
advantage of us. That's it. That's
all right.
Um okay. Naga head hunter says greetings
from Nagaland. Greetings. Uh recently uh
Isa Chishi son of lake Isak Chishi Swoo
joined hands with ousted NCIM leaders in
Burma. Will the US interfere like in the
case of
Kokilad?
Um okay that's an interesting question.
I'm not aware of what's happening there
in in Nagaland is at least uh all the
news has been about Manipur and the
disaster that's unfolding in Manipur and
lots of Naga people are also facing the
brunt of the of the invaders of the
illegal invaders the cookies um
so so Isato Chishi son of late uh
Isakishi Chishi Su joined hands with the
with ousted NCM leaders in Burma. Ah
okay that's interesting
um will the okay so I'm not aware of the
context over there uh but yes some NSN
IM and NSNK leaders would be in Burma I
suppose who would want to fight against
the government of India and that sort of
thing some kind of the context is there
will the US interfere like they are
interfering currently in the case of
Kiran look you give them the opportunity
they will interfere you give them an
inch they will take a mile the
Americans. So I hope the government of
India is keeping an eye I'm pretty sure
they are now at least keeping an eye on
the entire far east of India not just in
Manipur in Mizoram but also the entire
border with Burma north to
south and
uh the Americans would love to interfere
all over the place. So we will have to
be careful and I'm glad and I'm thankful
that you are raising this question and
bringing this to the notice of whoever
is watching and I hope the government of
India does the right thing and and takes
care of the interests of the natives of
the citizens and doesn't allow any more
interference by foreigners. That's what
I would
say. All
right. Okay. Chira Asti says, "Did
India's shift from an expansionist power
to a more neutral stance begin after
Ashoka's renunciation of conquest and
did this contribute to India's eventual
decline in global influence?" What do I
think? Okay. So, Ashoke was the great uh
unifier of India. It all started with
his
grandpa Chundra Gupta Moria and then you
had Binduar and then you had Ashok and
Ashoke expanded the empire to its
greatest
extent.
Um and uh yeah he unified India and the
whole subcontinent. He fought this great
war against Kolinga. Kolinga was
defeated. It was very bloody and then
his he stopped fighting because well
there was nobody else to fight. He had
no aspirations to go and conquer uh
let's say Bahalik or or Persia or
Greece. He said the subcontinent is
enough. No. So now let's be peaceful.
I've conquered everything. No more
fighting. And then uh yeah you could say
he renounced conquest because he had
conquered the whole subcontinent. Now
did this contribute to
India's decline in global influence?
That's an interesting question and let
me tell you why it didn't it's not the
case. So Ashok stopped conquering. Fine.
Okay. And after that the decline of the
empire starts the Moria Empire. And the
last emperor
is who was it? I forget. Sarati was it?
It was one of those guys. And then um
the last emperor was was so um let's say
not very capable that uh his sapati
Pisha Shunga had to assassinate him in
order to stabilize the the the
subcontinent. So then the Shunga Empire
starts and then you have other empires.
But did India stop expanding or did
India's emperors just renounce
expansionist expansionism after Ashoke?
Not quite the
case. For example, we had probably the
greatest emperor of all
Kaneshka who who had two capitals. One
was Matura and one was Purushpur which
is now called
Pishar. And he conquered an empire that
stretched from the shores of the Aral
Sea to the shores of the Caspian Sea. It
incorporated it encompassed the whole of
present day so-called Shinjang of
China. There was a gigantic empire that
he conquered
Kaneshka. He fought a lot of
foreigners. So
uh you do see some expansionism right
there don't you quite a bit of
expansionism a significant quite bit of
expansionism uh then you have um someone
like so so that's the Kushans then you
have other Kushan emperors Vasu deva who
again who kicked out the Chinese from
central Asia the Chinese are once again
trying to trying to make their way into
central Asia and Vasuva the Kushan
emperor emperor kicked them out of
central Asia so once again you have
expansionism there then you have Um when
you have the Gupta Empire, who was it?
Was it Kumar Gupta? Was it Chandra
Gupta? One of those two. He conquered
Bahalik. Bahalik is present day Balk
north of Afghanistan, that area. Um
Afghanistan was historically Gandhar,
but he went beyond that. Okay. So he
conquered lands beyond the subcontinent.
So once again there's expansionism
there. Um you had uh what's his name?
Samudra Gupta, right? the great
conqueror whose entire career as emperor
was one extended military campaign. So
there is there is expansionism there. So
there is the Gupta expansionism. Then
you have the Kota Empire.
[Music]
Um what's his name? Kota Empire. Who was
the king?
Kota
emperor Lal Lalita Lalita
Lala whose capital was
Shinagar he conquered large parts of
central Asia great
conqueror Lalita Muktapided so once
again you have a conqueror an
expansionist then you have the
Cholas uh Raj Rajar Raj Chola conquered
much of the subcontinent shore and Then
he while he was still alive he abdicated
his kingdom gave it to his son Rajendra
Chola and Rajendra Chola conquered
Southeast Asia all the way to the
Philippines. Is that not
expansionism? So you know we are
taught that after Ashoke we became all
pacifist and all soft and all all that.
It's complete
lie. We've had so many such I've just
given you a few few examples. I'm sure
there are more. Okay. So the point is
it's not the case what most of us
believe that after ashok renounced
violence and they renounced conquest,
India became a second rate world power
and nobody after no other king or
emperor dared to conquer beyond India
after that and we declined in global
influence. No, it's not quite the case.
It's much more complicated than than
that simplistic uh
worldview. Okay, let's see what else we
have. Okay, Malik says, "Why are there
no advanced unmanned underwater
submarines like we have in drones? If
India takes the lead in this, then it
can change naval warfare as it can be
cheap and very lethal if loaded with
explosives." That's a great point. And
you do have underwater unmanned
submersibles and submarines. You do have
that. Uh it's almost like underwater
drones. There are nations that are
developing those technologies. Uh let's
let's try and Google it. Okay. What what
does Google tell us? Let's find out.
Um
underwater
drones. So check it out. These are your
your your toys. Okay. Under unmanned
underwater under underwater vehicles. So
you had this history from the 1950s
onward 60s7s something happened in 2016.
Chinese warship seized an underwater
drone on in the process of being
retrieved to the US Navy. So you have
that okay various gliders manta ray kind
of thing applications in the militaries.
Say the US Navy began using UVs,
underwater and whatever vehicles in the
1990s to detect and disable underwater
underwater mines. The Chinese use it for
data collection and
reconnaissance and so much more. The
navies of multiple countries including
US, UK, France, India, Russia, China are
currently creating uncrrewed vehicles to
be used in oceanic warfare and so
on. So this has been going on for quite
a long time.
um you know these underwater
unmanned vehicles, drones, whatever you
want to call them. And they have all
kinds of military applications.
Uh they can
unleash explosives. They can they can
launch torpedoes. They can lay mines.
They can destroy mines. They can destroy
ships. They can be used for
reconnaissance. They can be used for
espionage. They can be used for for
cutting underwater cables, internet
cables. They can be used for all kinds
of purposes. And that technology has
been under development from the 1960s
onwards, 50s, 60s onwards. and all
self-respecting maritime nations,
military um self-respecting navies have
u such vehicles. So yeah, your your idea
is absolutely 100% correct and it is
something that uh has been worked on for
quite some time and you're absolutely
right. It can be very cheap and it can
be super lethal if uh used in the right
way militarily. Indeed.
Um Shri Ramachandra Nama says, "Do
snakes really save photos of humans in
their eyes?" Okay, now I have no idea
where that comes from. Snakes are uh
reptiles and reptiles have those slit
eyes, you know, slit eyes and they I'm
not sure if they view the world in color
or black and white, but I have no
evidence of them saving photos of humans
in their
eyes. I mean, how will they save a
photo? They would need some kind of
drive, right? Hard drive. U look, I'm
I'm being a little funny here, but no.
Uh there is no evidence of of any such
activity. Their brains are pretty
tiny and uh yeah the short answer is
they do not take photos of humans in
their
eyes. Okay. Arnav Javan says if we get a
political leadership like China and we
work 10 times harder, how many years or
decades will it take us to reach the
level of present day
China? 20
years.
20 not 10. 10 is too little. See the
Chinese they started their hard work in
the 19 late 1970s. It took them about
about a decade to figure things out.
It's in the 1990s. It's in late 80s and
1990s that that they put in place all
the programs the technological programs
and the most important thing was they re
was they re revamped their entire
education system to make it technolog
technologycentric and
forwardlooking. By revamping their
education system, they ensured that they
had the right talent going into the
universities. They made all the
universities research centric, research
oriented and they made the universities
feeder systems that would feed all the
technological research institutes, R&D
institutes with the brightest minds.
They created this whole system from the
bottom up and they invested trillions of
dollars into this thing. single-minded
long-term focus they had in the 1980s
and 1990s that by 2050 we'll be number
one. That's the kind of long-term
objective they had and they kept the
policy going year after year, decade
after
decade and today we are seeing the
effects of that of something that
started in the 1980s. So let's say it
starts in 1985 today it's 2025 that's 40
years took them 40 years. So if we get
the same sort of political leadership,
high quality leadership and if we work
10 times harder, it'll take us at least
20 years more. At least 20 years more.
Yeah. See, you see the magnitude of the
challenge in front of India. And the the
the truth is we don't have anything like
them. We have a a system that's 100
times worse and uh
etc. Okay.
Um Vun Prajapati says was the Roman
Empire the epitome of in humankind in
terms of the prosperity of citizens
military literature as we seen see the
romanization of that era in movies and
media movies and media are so powerful
they'll make you think the Roman Empire
was the greatest pinnacle of everything
in humankind the greatest prosperity of
citizens military literature etc. not
quite the case. It's all propaganda.
Look, the Roman Empire was great. It was
not a civilization. It was an
empire. It was an empire. There's a huge
difference between civilization and
empire. I'll go into the definition of
civilization all over again, but it's
not the same thing. There was
prosperity, but there
was,
look, in Rome, you had
slaves. Lots of
slaves. Lots of people were slaves.
Um and in a system where you have
slavery, you don't you can't quite say
that there was proper prosperity there.
If 10 20% of the population is enslaved
and your your your entire economy is
based on plunder and conquest of other
lands, then a small number of people
will be prosperous and everybody else
will be kind of under the boots of the
empire. And yes, they did impose pax
roana, Roman laws, Roman Roman language,
Latin all that over the place. and they
called it civilization but it was not
quite the same thing and lots of people
complained during the time that the
Romans they create a wasteland and then
they call it peace which means they
destroy everything and then they say
that we have pacified everything it's
not quite the
case okay so it was not the epitome of
prosperity in human history military
sure they had a tremendous
military and uh they conquered pretty
pretty decent amount of territory
um literature. What literature did the
Romans produce? A little bit of
literature. They copied most of the
Greek literature. Look, the Romans
didn't care much about culture and all,
but they did uh like culture and
appreciate to a certain extent. So,
whichever land they conquered, they
would take the literature from there and
they would take the gods from them. They
would worship those gods and and say the
literature is ours now. That's what they
would do. Okay? So they appropriated all
Greek literature. They appropriated all
Greek gods which were kind of already
Roman gods. Zeus Peter became Jupiter
become became Jupiter. Zeus Petro was
the Petro or Diopro who nobody in India
remembers today. Different story. So
look
propaganda says that wrote the Roman
Empire was the epitome and the pinnacle
of humankind now but it's not quite the
same. Not quite true. Not quite
true. Nothing against Rome. was
wonderful time I'm sure. But
um Kapalen says, "Is the universe finite
or infinite? Will we see a book tour
video?" Book tour video. I'm so lazy. I
don't make a book tour video. I've got
books all around me. I'll I'll do it one
of these days. Okay. Is the universe
finite or infinite? We don't have the
answer to the
question because there is something
called the observable universe. Okay.
There is an observable horizon of the
universe and that is about the diameter
of that it's like the universe the
observable universe is a perfect sphere
and we are the center of the sphere okay
and the diameter of the observable
universe is what 95 billion light years
that's the diameter of the observable
universe and the universe is expanding
so every single Today some portions of
of the universe go beyond the observable
horizon. They expand out of our reach.
We'll never see them again
ever. So there is a universe beyond the
observable horizon for sure. But how big
is that? We have absolutely no idea
because there's no way of knowing. We
have zero data out there of what's out
there. So we can't say maybe it's
infinite. Maybe it's finite. Maybe it's
like 10 times bigger than what we have
what we can see. Maybe it's a million
times bigger than what we can see. I
don't know. There's no way of answering
it in the absence of data. So that
question is out
there. Sparkling lotus says except goal.
Well, as long as aik and obelik are
there, you cannot take gold,
right? Who else was there?
Um the names were really funny.
dogmatics.
Dogmatics and I forget the names, but
yeah, good fun
names.
Um, okay, let's see some other
questions. Okay, Manu Krishna says, "I
love my nation as my own mother, but I'm
in a deep state of heartbreak because of
the country's current situation and what
she has endured. I can't even eat or
sleep properly. Please help.
See yeah India isn't in the best
state situation state of existence right
now uh we are definitely in a better
state of existence than maybe we were in
the
1600s definitely slightly better than
that
uh and we are definitely in a better
position than Gandhar was in let's
say 1000 AD
So you know there are times history
occurs in cycles. There are good times
and there are bad times like the le
ziplood say.
But there's no point sitting and
crying. Absolutely no point doing
that. What you can do is do your best to
contribute in whatever way is possible
to your motherland. Right? So if you are
sad that the situation is terrible and
there are things that you can't control,
yeah there are things beyond every
person has a set of things he or she can
control, small set of things and
everything else is beyond their control.
So what you can do as a
person is take whatever is within your
control and try and create something
positive with that and if you have the
wherewithal then try and make more
things within your control and try and
be a positive influence on all all of
that and if everybody starts doing that
then you know the situation turns
around. So I would recommend don't be
all
heartbroken. Sleep well, eat well and do
something constructive. Do something
positive with your existence, with your
life. And if and and inspire more people
to do that. And if everyone contributes
whatever they can in their own small or
big way and if everybody works hard like
that works together towards a common
purpose towards a common objective of of
improving the condition of our country
then things will
change. So the problem is that most
Indians don't even
see everybody else as part of the same
team. That's the biggest problem in
India.
We simply don't see that we are one
people, one nation. We have one purpose
because nobody identifies, nobody
defines, none of our leaders defines
what is the purpose of
India? What is the big objective of
India? What is our
mission? Does any leader today tell you
that this so and so is India's mission?
By 2040 we have to achieve this. By 2050
we have to achieve this. I have heard
slogans and all that stuff but you have
to be a nations that's that's laser
focused on a certain purpose. What's the
nation's motto
slogan? If you look at the the people in
the country they are living out the
opposite mo
mottoy
right. So India needs to
have India needs to have a mission, a
purpose, a a time frame, purpose,
mission with deadlines. And everybody
needs to feel like they are all part of
a mission. They have to all work
together. We are all a team. You meet a
stranger somewhere, you should know,
even though you not don't know the
person, you should feel like, yeah, we
are even though we are strangers, we
never met, but we are all part of the
same team. We are working in the same
direction. that is missing in the
country. So let's all find some purpose
for ourselves and for our country and
all work towards that in our own way. So
one person can be an artist, one person
can be a scientist, one person can be an
engineer, one can be a teacher, one can
be a bureaucrat, let's say. So you're
all working in very different domains.
But if you're all trying your best to
improve the situation of your country,
you're all working in the same
direction. That's what needs to happen.
So there's no point sitting and crying
and being all heartbroken and not
sleeping and not
eating. Get up, stand up, and and and do
something about
it.
Um, okay. What else do we have? What
other questions? IMG says, "Can aliens
manipulate our satellite images to give
false information about their universe?
This can help alien civilization to hide
from other civilizations. Well, if I was
an alien, I would love to do such
things. You know, if I was an alien, I
was I was if I was the leader of an
alien civilization, I would tell my
minions, go out there everywhere,
wherever there are humans or other
planets, you go and meddle with the
satellites, give them false information,
and make them think they're allowed in
the universe. Completely fool them.
Look, I don't know the answer to your
question, but if aliens exist, maybe
they can do it. Do aliens exist? We have
no evidence of that. Can aliens exist?
Certainly, it's possible. It's quite
possible that aliens may exist, that you
may have other life forms in other parts
of the universe, in other parts of the
galaxy, maybe in our solar system as
well. Who knows? We don't know. It's
possible. Um, so hypothetically,
theoretically, it's possible and so on.
Yeah. Okay.
Xmus Zeus says, "Let's have a math
podcast for
fun." I wonder how many people will
watch that ma math podcast. I don't mind
having a math podcast. I love math. I
love complicated math. I love advanced
math. But uh I think if I make such a
podcast, the viewership will be very
low. After one year, it'll have like
3,000
views. Most people don't want to see
math. They don't like math. I think it
it most people are scared of math,
right? And so on. So yeah, I I don't
mind it really. Find me a good
mathematician. I'll do a podcast. I love
doing podcast on things I enjoy, even if
nobody cares, even if nobody wants to
watch. So yeah, find me a good
mathematician. I'll do a math
podcast.
Uh, right. What next? What next?
Um okay Sergeant Skylin says do you
think India can replace China in the
export of rare rare earth
materials? How
much do we have sufficient quantities of
these rare earth
minerals? I think China it accounts for
the export of 90% of the global supply
of rare earths.
And uh I hear that India had discovered
reasonable deposits of these things but
I'm not sure. I think look what I think
is that India is a gigantic place. I
don't think so. I know that India is a
gigantic subcontinent. Tremendous amount
of natural resources are just lying
underground. I'm sure we have sufficient
quantities of everything. Whether it's
rare earths, whether it's uranium,
whether it's oil and gas. I I think we
have not even started looking. It's just
like the archaeology situation. We have
more than 2,000 undiscovered unexplored
archaeological sites on the on the dry
river banks of just one ancient river,
the
Saraspati. Just on the on the river
river banks of just one ancient river,
we have more than 2,000 untouched
archaeological sites. Similarly, all
across the length and breadth of India,
I'm pretty sure there's more than enough
mineral wealth to completely make India
self-sufficient. Whether it's oil,
whether it's gas, whether it is whatever
else, rare earths, I don't think we have
even begun to look
properly. Uh but yeah, there's no point
of having potential unless you use the
potential.
uh so unless we go out and we prospect
we discover things we will never know
what we have so theoretically I'm sure
we can do it but are we looking for it
have we made the discoveries I'm not
quite sure I remember a couple of years
ago we dis it came in the news we have
discovered the world's second largest or
something deposits of
lithium in two three places one was in
Jammu Kashmir so that was like at least
a year ago what action has been taken
to extract the lithium. What has been
done? I am not sure anything has been
done. So that's the kind of country
India India is that we simply don't take
action. If action is taken, there's a
whole lengthy procedure tender you have
to do tenders and there's a procedure
you have to do and there's L1 and L2 and
God knows it takes decades to to move a
single piece of paper somewhere in
India.
So if India stays like that, remains
like that, then we will never replace
China. But if we do the right thing,
then we can replace China.
So
okay, what other
questions? Sonu Barav says, "Please call
Mr. Barav for a math podcast." Well, I
would love to. Yeah, let me try and
reach out to him. It'll be fun. Yeah, I
would love to. Great, great
recommendation. Let's try and let me try
and see if I can can reach out to Mangul
Fields medal winner. Amazing
guy. Okay. Shubam Ramola says, "Every
year thousands of high netw worth
individuals migrate out of India and how
does it affect affect our economy in the
long run? Why isn't the government doing
anything to halt it? So why do net high
netw worth individuals migrate out of
India? You to ask yourself that question
first of all. Why do wealthy Indians
feel the need to leave
India? There must be something in India
that makes them want to leave India.
Right?
Well, you know, if you if you are a high
net worth person, HNI, high netw worth
individual, then you you will be running
a business or you'll have a large amount
of money and you will have to pay taxes
on that and the taxes will be very high
and then the the point is if you are
spending so much money paying so many
taxes then what do you get in exchange
in return for that? Do you get a high
quality of life? Do we get do we get the
facilities we would get in a first world
country? You don't get any of that.
Let's say you're running a business.
Let's say you you have 10,000 crores in
your bank account and you want to run a
business. Well, running a business is so
difficult in India compared to running a
business elsewhere. And it's so
frustrating and it's so painful that
eventually you say, "Okay, I'll I'm just
going to give up give up. I'll go
somewhere else and I'll take my business
elsewhere." The system is like that.
Nobody hates the country. Nobody hates
the culture. Nobody hates the people.
the system, the parasitical system that
is leeching the the the lifeblood of the
country. That is the
problem. And to to fix that, we
need deep
reforms. And when when will those
reforms happen? We don't
know. Um so yeah, it's it's an issue.
See, high netw worth individuals leave
the country. uh the brightest minds
leave the country and go abroad. Who is
developing all the AIS in the US? A lot
of Indians are there. A lot of Indians
are at the forefront of the development
of artificial intelligence systems, LLM
and whatnot in the United
States. Much of it is being done by
Indians. The same Indians who were once
here and they chose to leave the country
because the country doesn't treat them
the way they should be treated.
The country doesn't uh value merit. The
country doesn't value talent. The
country seeks to destroy talent. The
education system hunts down and destroys
talent and it rewards mediocrity. Who
wants to live in such a
system? And you should see some sign of
reform at some point in time. What
reform has happened? So people leave the
country for these reasons and you can't
blame them for that. Some of them end up
bitter and some of them end up hating
their country. Some of some of them
understand that the country is not at
fault. It's the system. It's the people
who run the system who are at fault.
Those people are the they will ensure
the system never changes because they
benefit from the
system. So how does it affect the
economy in the long run? Obviously it
affects the
economy. Um if those people those high
net worth net worth individuals were to
remain in India set up businesses run
them successfully then it would be great
for the economy. It would make the
economy boom. If talented people were to
remain in India and use their talent in
the service of the nation it would be
great for the country. So all those all
those people going out of the country
it's it's a net loss for India. It's a
huge loss. It's an ongoing huge loss
year after year for
India and something has to be done to
arrest this. Since I was a little kid, I
have been hearing about brain drain.
Well, what has any leader ever done
about brain drain to to stop the brain
drain in this country? It's very simple.
You have to create a system that's
meritocratic. You should not victimize
talented people. But that's what happens
in this country. So the country suffers
as a result. And uh
yeah.
Okay.
Uh anonymous scientist says, "Do you
like the Beatles? Then which Beatles
song is your favorite?" I've never been
a great fan of the
Beatles. I never quite got what's the
big deal about the
Beatles. Um they did have some good
songs. What? Norwegian Wood is good.
Norwegian Wood. I'm sure there are other
other good songs as well, but
uh yeah, I I never found them
really very interesting. There were
other bands that were that were
definitely much more interesting for
me. Naven Kumar says, "Being a happy
idiot is better than becoming a
miserable genius." Do you agree?
Maybe you're right. But I guess you
don't get a choice in this matter,
right? If you are an idiot, let's say
hypothetically, let's say hypothetically
if I'm an idiot, then it's not my choice
to be an idiot or not. I think it
happens because you are born with a
certain IQ bandwidth that the maximum IQ
you will ever have in your life is this
much and the lowest you will ever have
is hopefully limited to some level and
you will operate in that in that in that
range. I think it's genetic it's what
not
whatever. So if you are born with a
certain set of genes which gives you a
certain range of IQ in which you can
operate and let's say that IQ range is
80 to 100 for example I don't know what
is the idiot level IQ right what is it
80 is it 70 let's say it's 70 to 80 for
example hypothetically then I think you
may be classified as what they call an
idiot so it's not a choice that you
have you you're dealt a certain set of
cards in your life and you're going to
live with that. So, if you're an idiot
and if you're happy, well, good for you,
bro. That's what I'll say. And is it is
it is it true that geniuses are
miserable? Well, once again, it's a
choice to be happy or to be miserable.
If you're a genius, you'll understand
the world much better than other people.
And the deeper the more you understand
the world, the more you see all the
nasty things that the world is filled
with. And you see a lot of the truth
about a lot of
people. Yeah. All that you see. And uh
it it can make you cynical. It can make
you somewhat miserable at times. But at
the end of the day, it's your choice. Do
you want to be happy? Do you want to
miserable? I'm sure there are happy
geniuses too out there. I think you know
the the real
measure of how intelligent you are and
how gen how much of a genius you are.
Look, if you are a genius, you should be
able to get what you want,
right? Are you able to get what you
want? If you are a genius, if if let's
say a person is a genius, but he or she
has
not got
acquired what they want in life, then
how can you call them a genius?
Just having high intelligence doesn't
make you genius. Doesn't make you a
genius. You should be able to
uh use that
intelligence to achieve whatever
outcomes you want in life. And I think
that's what you would call
a what you would categorize as a real
genius. Yeah. We we hear all these
stories of the tormented geniuses, you
know, the great authors. Vincent Van Go
the greatest poet of the greatest
painter of all
time but he was never recognized as such
during his lifetime and he he died
penniless poor and sad tormented
u so yeah he had that incredible talent
and that was not his fault but I would
say if you're a real genius all round
genius you should be able to achieve
what you want in life and then you will
not be miserable
um so what is better. I think what is
best is to be a happy
genius. I think that's I'm sure that's
that's much better than being a happy
idiot. But I'm sure being a happy is
also great. A life of
bliss. Life of life of complete
ignorance and complete bliss. Everything
is fine. Everything is fun. Everybody is
my friend. Everyone's good. I mean
that's also a nice life I would say. So
yeah, it depends.
It depends on the
person. All right.
[Music]
Um, okay. Yes. Parik says, "I just came
to know about the battle of Dwire. Being
a Rajasthan, I was shocked that I never
knew about it. Could you please tell us
something about it? Why were we never
taught
this?" Well, I am shocked. I don't know
about this. I don't know what this is.
Battle of the Wire. I'm I'm I myself
have not read about this.
So, I can't tell you anything about it,
but I will try and look it up. I'll not
do the research right now because then
I'll be quiet. I'll be reading. But,
okay.
Interesting. Let me just quickly Google
that and and just figure out what that
is. Battle of the W. Let's see. Okay,
let's let's do that.
Battle of
Diwir. So this was between Diwir between
okay a significant conflict in the
ongoing Rajput Mogul conflict 1606. It
pitted the force of Amar Singh of Bir
against the Mgul army led by Janir
uh etc etc. It resulted in a victory for
Amar Singh marking a crucial moment in
the resistance against Mgul
expansion. Okay that's interesting. I am
not aware of it and um okay I'll I'll
check it out. I'm not aware of it. Thank
you for bringing this to my notice and
our
notice. Vikram Geopolitical says when
thinking about polymaths the name of
Raindra Nath Tagore doesn't come to our
mind. He was also a great polymath. What
are your views about him? I don't know
much about Ravindraat Tagore. I'm I
haven't read any of his works. I haven't
read about his life life story etc. I
know that he was awarded the Nobel Prize
in literature for uh a book or or or or
or a work called
Gangjali. I know that he was a poet and
a writer and the the the the originator
of what they call Rabindra
Sangeit and to be a polymath you have to
be a top
quality exponent in multiple
fields. So for example they give the
name of Leonardo da Vinci. Leonardo da
Vinci was a great pointer painter a
great uh sculptor. He was an inventor
you could say a scientist. He was an
anatomist. So he was a top
quality practitioner of of anatomy of of
uh let's say engineering or
invention of of uh painting of of
sculpture. So that's a true polymath.
Someone who is great at multiple fields.
Do we have other examples of polymaths?
Let let's let's try and figure it out.
The person who is genuinely good at so
many multiple things. Let's
see.
Polymaths. Who were polymaths? M A T
math. So give me some names. Leonardi
Aristotle.
Uh Isaac
Newton, Rabbindra Tagore, poet, writer,
social reformer, philosopher,
playwright, artist. Okay, good. Hipatia
of Alexandria and so on and so on. Okay.
So, yeah, look, I I'm not really very
familiar with the works and life of
Rabida Tagore, so I can't really comment
much about it, but uh yeah, it's good to
know that he was a polymath and yeah,
great that we have one of one of our
people in that
list. Um Romesh Ay says India should
hold ATP, WTA Masters 10,000 or at least
a 500 event. What are your thoughts? I
think we should hold all kinds of events
in the sporting world in India. We
should have our own grand slam in tennis
or at least something as good as a grand
slam. We should have Why don't we
popularize the sport of rugby in India?
We are good at kabadi. Kabadi is a very
physical game. It's a contact sport. All
you have to do is add some running into
it and you have rugby with a weird
shaped ball.
Players who are good at kobi will
naturally be good at rugby. Why can't we
popularize something like rugby? You
know, you need some of that in life,
especially if you're a male. Little bit
of jousting. So, I would love to have
rugby in India. Why don't we have a
rugby premier league in India? Why don't
we have a basketball league in India?
Multiple basketball. Why don't we have a
hockey league like the IPL in India?
Hockey is supposedly our national sport.
Why don't we have
that? I just don't get it why we don't
have these things.
Um why don't we have a volleyball league
like that in India? We there are so many
sports out there. We can popularize all
the sports. We can create whole economic
ecosystems around these sports. We could
be a major global sporting power just if
a few people would would invest in these
leagues you know create these leagues.
You can't expect the government to do
all these things. I know government also
sometimes comes in the way with their
sporting sports associations and all
that. politicians are part of that and
all but yeah I completely agree with you
we should have all these events in India
and it's it's I think it's a low
lowhanging
fruit you can create a whole economic
infrastructure and ecosystem around
these things because if you have a sport
that is popular then you will have lots
of athletes which means you need lots of
coaches you will need lots of support
staff lots of medical personnel you will
need um infrastructure as in stadiums
and training facilities
and you know a whole economic ecosystem
can be constructed around any any
particular sport and if you have like
like 20 sports that are popular in the
in that manner imagine today I mean when
the IPL happens Indians forget
everything and the whole nation stops
because Indians don't have any other
avenue of entertainment beyond cricket
why not make other sports more popular
and you know sports sporting success
brings n the nation
together. It's only when you achieve
great success uh in sports or or in
other fields that the nation comes
together. Nothing unifies a nation like
success in the international domain and
sports is a great place to to have this.
It's a great substitute for war. Sports
is a substitute for
warfare. So you know we should we should
do these things. We should we should
have that. If I had a few billion
dollars, I would certainly do invest in
all these
things. Uh Mr. 88 says, "Why is Japan
offering its E5 and E3 Shinkansen trains
for free? Those are older models." Okay,
so listen, when you set up a new track,
you need a couple of tester trains,
trains to test out the track and do some
some routine work. So the the trains
that will actually run on these tracks
will be the E8 or E10 or whatever the
the series is. But they are offering a
couple of these trains for free just for
the testing purpose. I think when Taiwan
set up its Shinkansen line, the Japanese
gave at least one train to the Taiwanese
also for free like that. So it's just u
it's a nice gesture and we certainly
appreciate that.
Geopolitical Dubai says was Kishor Kumar
a genius singer and did you listen to
him? I think he was probably my favorite
male singer uh in Hindi songs. I mean
yeah probably but of course you should
be sure you should know I mean genius I
mean he had a great voice and he was a
great actor too actually and for some
reason he stopped acting after after
that movie the comedy movie with Saira
Banu and u
sur what's the name of that movie let's
let's
Posen was it Posen
uh let's
see kishure Kumar Pu son I think it was
yeah it was the last movie in which he
acted. He was an absolute genius at
comedy and other stuff also and he was a
great
singer and uh but you should know that
you know what is that
song om shantiom right kishor kishor
kumar om
shantiom so this song om shantiom okay
I'm sure everyone is aware of
Yes. Well, let me tell you what's the
original
song. Original song. Mary Omar, no
javano, etc., etc. What is the original
song? Om Shanti Om
uh West
Indies I'm not able to I can't remember
the the copied song, right?
Bollywood song copied Om Shanti Om
copied from okay let's
[Music]
um so there was this guy I forget his
name he was from the West
Indies Lord
Shorty Shorty I don't know why Google
won't find it okay Lord Shorty it's the
same song infringement of copyright so
there was a song by a Trinidadian soa
artist Lord Shorty
which Kush and Kushar Kumar went to the
Caribbean. He met this guy Lord Shorty
and Lord Shorty played that song for him
and then we finds out that next year
Kushar Kumar has released that song in a
Bollywood movie. So that's the kind of
thing Mr. Kusher Kumar did which is sad
to see because I was a big fan of him
but you know yep it is what it is.
Yes.
Ouch.
Okay. Uh yeah, enough enough controversy
for one day. Let's let's not get into
let's not into get into AR Rahman and
all
that.
Uh Priyang Shu says, "Could you please
share your email ID? I'm working on
Indo-Pacific region. I'm willing to
interact with you. Could you
give Listen, I don't know why people
find it so hard to contact me. Has
anybody ever bothered to look at the
description of my
videos? My email ID is
there. Why don't people take a little
bit of initiative and do a little bit of
searching? Look in the description of
this video. My email is there. Shouldn't
be that hard to find to to re to reach
out to
me. Sam says, "Is intelligence genetic
or
developed?" I think there is that's a
question of nature and nurture. Right?
Look, I
believe from a little bit of
understanding and experience, more than
a little bit, I would say that there are
two components to intelligence. One is
inherited.
There's an inherited component and then
there is an a developed component. So
some people are just
born more intelligent and some people
are just born less
intelligent. You can't deny
that. And if you are born with a certain
which means that everybody who when they
are born they their genetic encoding is
such that you will be able to operate
within a certain range of intelligence
lower range and upper range. So maybe
someone has a lower range of 100 IQ.
Okay, I'm just giving a hypothetical
range. So someone's lower range will be
100 IQ and maybe upper range will be 125
for example. That's decent IQ. So if
that person is completely lazy and
doesn't bother to study and doesn't
bother to hone their intelligence,
they'll operate at level 100. But if
they really study and they really
develop their mind and exercise their
mind and sharpen their intellect, then
they'll be able to operate at 125. But
they won't be able to go beyond 125
because that's the limitations of of
that's the genetic limitations that
that's the limitation encoded in their
genetics. So yes, some of it is genetic
and some of it is developed. So you are
dealt a certain set of genetic cards and
you it means that you're capable of of a
range of things and if you really work
hard on it then you can operate at the
upper upper end upper end of the range
of your intelligence. So it's both it's
genetic as well as developed. So if a
person has that range of 100 to 125,
they will never be able to operate I
believe at 140 or 150, right? But yeah,
you may be able to operate at 80 if you
if you want if you Yeah, that that
that's possible I
suppose.
Um Nad Rooney says, "Can you know Japan?
Can you speak a Japanese? I been started
learning Japan a help. I don't want you
motivation. Okay, listen. I don't know
how to speak Japanese. Uh Japanese, I'm
sure is a wonderful language. It's a
wonderful culture. One of my favorite
nations, cultures in Asia, but I don't
speak Japanese. I've never tried to
learn Japanese. I may know a few words
here and there. I know a few words here
and there of almost every language. A
couple of words here and there. Uh, but
it doesn't mean I know the language. So,
yeah, I don't know Japanese, but uh,
yeah, I'm I'm glad that you're learning
Japanese and all the best for that.
Romeshay says, "How different is Swiss
German from traditional German?" I don't
really really know. I lived in
Switzerland for a while as a kid, but
the the language I was familiar with was
French. I lived in the Swiss, the
western part of Switzerland, and that's
where you speak
French. And I can tell you the
difference differences between Swiss
French and French French, but I don't
quite know the difference between Swiss
German and traditional German.
Um, yeah. Yeah. I'm I'm not I'm not
quite sure what the differences are.
there are some subtle differences but in
French when it comes to French
um so for example
um yeah in for example in French for the
word
80 in in France they say tis which means
7010 okay but in Switzerland they say
kathma which means 420s so 20* 4 so they
say kathma in in Switzerland in in in
France they say
sept so 70 so 88 would be septant dwit
in in France but kthit in in in
Switzerland so there's a difference
subtle difference between Swiss French
and French French but I'm not quite sure
what the difference between Swiss German
and traditional German is but there is
some there are some small subtle
differences but I never learned German I
think there was one year in which I had
to learn like some basic German in in
class but uh it never took root in me. I
think I I understood more general ger
German later on. I learned I got to
understand a bit more German later on
because I discovered the the
similarities between German and English
because English is a Germanic
language. Uh yeah, but I I don't quite
know. All
right. Okay. Josh Gon says, "Do you
think India can move out of democracy
which we know is a facade only leading
to a five-year tunnel vision of leaders
to stay in power? If yes, how the how
can that happen? I have absolutely no
idea how you can transition out of a
democracy. And especially in India where
you have a great der of highquality
leaders, if India transitions into a
dictatorship, you may have even worse
leaders becoming
dictators. Okay. So yeah you know
theoretically if you look back at
history all our kings and emperors were
from today's perspective dictators
obviously right um Nepo kids you could
say because they were the sons of of
previous kings and so on that's how it
is to work in dynasties so technically
from today's worldview perspective kings
and emperors were dictators but they
operated in a different way they
operated within the confines of dharma
and they were not quite dictators they
had councils of ministers would advise
them and people could actually censor
kings, censure kings and kings could
even be thrown out of power by citizens
if they did not well abide by dharma and
so on. So we had checks and balances of
our own kind of of our civilizational
variety back in the day. Today you don't
have any of that. So if today you end up
having a dictatorship in India, it may
it may end up being like a like an
African country dicty
dictatorship. Uh and I'd rather not want
that. So I don't know. It's a very
difficult way forward for India. The
system that we are laboring under is
terrible. It's it's eminently unsuitable
for India. It's not going to take India
forward in the right direction. It's
going to you know relegate India in the
realm of mediocrity for for as long as
it lasts. But how do you come out of
this? I'm not quite sure. You would need
an exceptionally
uh strong leader of incredible fortitude
to be able to single-handedly turn the
system around, take the bull by the
horns and change the whole system. Um
very hard to see that happening but it
can happen. It's happened in the past. I
mean lots of examples. An example I
could give which is not which may not be
very appropriate but I can think of the
example of Mustafa Kimal Taturatur in
Turkey who
did almost the impossible. He turned an
ancient Islamic country into a modern
secular dictatorship of kinds you know
into a modern nation.
Um, so it may be possible, but you would
need a person of incredible
fortitude to be able to do that. Do we
have anything anyone like that on the
horizon today? I'm not quite
sure.
Uh, Moonlight Sonata says, uh, can you
please tell us why the US doesn't want
to sell the F22 Raptor even after having
the kill switch, but it's willing to
sell the successor F-35. The F22 Raptor,
I don't think they'll sell to anyone.
Have they exported it to anybody at all?
The F-22 is the best aircraft. Let me
Google this. Okay, let me see if the
F-22 has been exported. Has the F22
been been
exported? There we have it. The jet
fighter so advanced that US law bans it
from being
exported. Like I said, it's the most
advanced fighter they have. It it is way
better than the F-35. The
F-35 it's like a fine it's like a flying
coke can. Okay. The F-35 the F-22 is a
beast of an aircraft. It's the best
aircraft they have. And yeah, they won't
export it. It is so advanced and it's so
capable that you can't give it in in
anyone's hands. You can't even give it
to your own allies. That's how good the
aircraft is. Even even if there's a kill
switch, you don't just don't you see you
don't want people to have that thing in
their hands. Whether it's a kill switch
or a back door or whatever they they put
in there doesn't matter. So yeah, I
think they've they've built this F-35
for multiple purposes. One could be
moneyaundering perhaps, one could be to
enrich the military-industrial complex
and the people who run that and also
they've made multiple
variants. Some of them are to be
exported. Some of some of them are
designed to be
exported. Amisha says what's cooking
between Pakistan and Bangladesh. Look,
when you have two vasals of the big
boss, they'll talk to each
other. So, East Pakistan, West Pakistan
are both nations that have had a regime
change operation done upon them by the
United States. In Pakistan, it happened
in 2022 when Imran Khan was ousted. He
was pro-China. He was ousted and whoever
came to power, whoever was put in that
seat is now I think it's Sharif, right?
Shabbaz Sharif. He is a pro- US uh
person and Pakistan is now a pro- US
regime. It's a US Vasal. And same thing
happened to Bangladesh. Shikhasina who
was pro- India let's say she was ousted
and uh whatever regime is in power there
is is pro- US today so the two are both
minions of the United States so they
will coordinate together and recently
the Pakistani foreign minister or
whatever that person is she visited
Bangladesh and she met with the puppet
guy Yunus Muhammad
Yunus and they will try and cook
something together obviously to with
with an eye on India. Uh not quite sure
what it will be. Uh but there could be
military cooperation between the between
the two
nations. Uh Muhammadus has been trying
to bring China into the mix. Um not
quite sure the Americans will like that
very much because uh you know China is
enemy number one for them. So yeah,
something is cooking and we over here
we're going to have to be really
careful. So we now have the same old
two-front situation. East Pakistan, West
Pakistan.
Okay. Uh Sabaria says, "Who exactly are
Caucasians?" Well, let's go to the map
and I'll tell you who really are the
Kauazians.
Okay.
Um let's go to the
map and here we
are. So this is the map. The Caucasian
people are the people who are the
natives and inhabitants of the Caucasus
region. What is the Caucasus region?
Okay, start from where we are. India, we
know where India is. Go westwards. Go
westwards. You cross the artificial
temporary nation. You you cross Gandhar.
You cross Persia. uh you come into
Mesopotamia from Mesopotamia from
Baghdad you go northwards north north
you cross Armenia Azarbaijan and that's
the Caucasus region the region between
the black sea and the Caspian sea that
is the Caucasus region and the people
who live in the Caucasus region are the
Caucasian people and this was
historically considered to be the the
artificial dividing line between Europe
and Asia
uh the Caucasus region the Caucasus
mountains right so you have regions like
um countries and regions like Armenia,
Georgia, uh Dagistan, Cheschna,
etc. In the Caucasus region, uh the
people of the Caucasus region are
ethnically Indo-Iranian or Iranic
origin. people they they're called. You
have languages like the Oetian language
and the Iran language that are spoken
here that are related to ancient
Skyian and that's the Caucasus region
and that's the Caucasus people and um
today uh Caucasian is used as the name
of a race the white race. So the white
people are called Kauasian
people because some somebody in the 19th
century or somewhere believed that the
white race originated from the Kauasus
region.
So that's that's a pseudoscientific
completely wrong term. But the real
Caucasian people are the people who live
in that region the Kauasus region the
Kavkas Kavkas
region. Um Chiraavasi says do you think
despite not born not being born in India
was Kaneshka the great more Indian in
spirit than many Indians today? Kanesha
was born in India.
his
ancestors came from. Okay, let's go to
the
map. So once again we open the map and
let's talk
about a certain period of
history. So if you go let's say you are
in the far east of India let's say
you're in Manipur. Okay Manipur let's go
straight north of Manipur just straight
north. So you cross Arunachal Pradesh,
you cross Tibet, you keep going north,
you keep going north, you keep grow
going north and where do you reach? You
reach
Mongolia. Just go straight north of
Manipur, you will reach eventually
Mongolia. So this region, the Mongolia
region about 2 and a half thousand years
ago. In this region, there used to
be a tribal confederation who lived
here. They were called by the Chinese.
The Chinese they called them the Shyu,
the Shyu
tribe. They were the ancestors of the
Huns and the
Mongols. The Houns eventually became the
Turks. Kind of. Okay, just making it
oversimplifying it, but that's kind of
what happened. The Huns eventually
became the
Turks. So over here you had the Shau or
the Hunik people who originated
somewhere around this region, today's
Mongolia region.
And west of that region you had the
whole of the central Asian uh
grasslands and you had Tibet and present
day East Turkiststan Shinjang all that.
Now in north of Nepal, north of India in
this region which is present day Tibet
and present day Shing Jang, you had a
people who were probably the descendants
of the Tushara people of the Mahabharat,
the Tokaran people and they were called
they were a confederation of multiple
tribes. One of the tribes was called the
Kushan tribe. So when the huns when the
shau they expanded westwards from
present day Mongolia region
they caused the Kushans and the other
tribes of the region to flee westwards.
So these tribes they fled westwards and
the schithians who were living north of
India they to flee into India to escape
from the
Kusans. So you had an akitian invasion
of India during the Indo- Greek era and
a couple of centuries later the Kushans
followed them into India. The Kushads
also invaded India. So Kaneshka's
ancestors were part of the confederation
that invaded India. Now who were the
Kushans originally? They were Indo-Ier
Indo-Uropean people. They were
essentially of Indian origin, but they
had been living outside of India for
several centuries or maybe several
thousand years.
Um and and you know if you look at if
you look at the Tarim basin mummies who
are found in that region the ancestral
homeland of the Kushans they look like
Europeans. They are like 6 and 1/2 ft
tall. Some of them some of them have
have red hair. Some of them have blonde
hair and their skin is whitish or
something but their genetics is R1 A1A
mostly which is Indian. So it's weird.
And they used to worship Indian
gods. Um and there are cities in that
region which are under the sands now.
cities that were discovered by
Orurelstein, the great explorer,
Hungarian British explorer, cities like
Dandan, Oilik and whatnot where you
still find uh you know representation of
representations of Indian gods and all
that. So the Kushans eventually entered
India and they were genetically
culturally quite similar to us and they
took over large parts of India and the
invaders were Kaneshka's ancestors but
Kaneshka was most likely born somewhere
in northern India. His ancestors were
you could say invaders or immigrants. So
he was a third, second, third, fourth
generation immigrant or whatever you
want to call him.
But if you look at Keshka's actions, he
was more Indian than any other any other
leader of today. I'll tell you
that he was definitely more more Indian
than than Ashoke. Sorry, not Ashoke.
What?
Akbar Kaneshka did more than any other
Indian emperor to spread Indian culture
far and wide beyond India.
He he spread India's territories,
expanded India's territories in all
directions. He took care of the Indian
national interest, cultural interest,
civilizational interest like nobody
before or after. And he spread India's
he was the guy who who spread Indian
culture and civilization
eastwards. It eventually ended up
reaching Japan, South Korea all the way
through China. Kaneshka is the guy who
started this and he patronized every
Indian god. If you look at his
coinage, 5% of his coinage has the
Buddha. 95% of the coinage has all the
other gods and goddesses. Lots of Shiva,
lots of coins with Lord Shiva on them,
Nandi on them, some with Aurora Mazda on
them. He worshiped every god who was a
truly Indian guy. So Kaneshka was
Kaneshka the great one of our greatest
emperors of all time. Certainly one of
my favorite emperors. I wish we had
someone like him today. Kaneshka the
great.
Okay. Okay. Let's uh what does Vidhi
have to say? Does genetics and nervous
system engineering does it have anything
to do with language? Do you think
Sanskrit will be more helpful to the
students while learn with learning
disabilities instead of
English? Interesting question. some
languages are better for the nervous
system for the brain apparently than
other languages. Uh so I'm not sure
about I mean I don't think anybody has
done any research about what would be
the effect of learning Sanskrit on
somebody who has a learning disability.
I don't think anybody has done that sort
of research scientific research in a
proper uh scientific manner. I'm not
sure anyone has done that. What I know
is that there is something called a
sanskrit effect. So let me let's Google
that together.
And that is scientific research.
Um the Sanskrit
effect. So it's a theory proposed by
neuroscientist James Hartzel saying that
suggesting that memorizing and reciting
Sanskrit mantras enhances brain regions
associated with cognitive function
particularly memory and language.
Studies have shown that professionally
qualified Sanskrit pundits exhibit
increased gray matter density and
cortical thickness in key brain regions
compared to control groups. This
suggests that the rigorous memorization
and recitation practice associated with
Sanskrit mantras may lead to measurable
changes in brain structure and
function. Sanskrit effect scientific
American
uh and so on so forth. So I think that
I'm not sure where it is. There's a lot
of this blog post and all that they
define but I there are at least I'm sure
that there is some published research on
this like peer-reviewed research on the
Sanskrit effect. So yes now does it mean
that if you memorize any any language
large quantities of text in any language
will it have the same effect on your
brain? I don't know. No one's tried to
compare do a comparative study of
memorizing copious amounts of Sanskrit
mantras versus let's say memorizing
something in Latin similar quantity of
whatever in Latin I'm not sure anybody
has done that so I can't you know I
can't comment on that but I think
Sanskrit is and there is something it's
also said that you know
u chanting Sanskrit or or listening to
Sanskrit create has a kind of meditative
effect on the mind calms you down and
and brings your anxiety levels down and
all that just by either chanting
something in Sanskrit whether you
understand or not just the the pattern
of the sounds is such that it calms you
down or just listen to somebody doing
that that will calm you down and it
it'll create a meditative kind of effect
in your mind so there seems to be
something about about Sanskrit that's
different from other languages I wish
Indian scientists Indian researchers
would take this up but it's other people
are doing it James Hardzel
our scientists, our academics, our
researchers have no interest in doing
any of these things and that is so sad
to see. So it looks like there is
something special about the Sanskrit
language and I would be happy if
somebody would try it out
um and and try and see whether Sanskrit
will have a positive effect on students
who have learning
disabilities at least it cannot harm
them. So why don't you do a structured
experiment and and see if if there is
some positive effect of that. It'll be
great if somebody does that sort of
experiment you know but yeah or it looks
like Sanskrit there is something special
about this one language
Sanskrit. Okay Anant is asking a
question what is
this China looks like a fan of Donald
Trump are you
Anand?
Okay. So the question is Tibet USA vasal
if China didn't capture it. China China
I think what he's asking is that if
China did not capture Tibet would Tibet
have become an American
vasal? Well it's a hypothetical
question. U if China did not capture
Tibet well in what under what conditions
would we have a world in which China did
not capture Tibet? That would happen
only if India was strong enough to
defend Tibet and safeguard Tibet's
sovereignty. So if India was strong
enough to prevent China from capturing
Tibet because if India wasn't strong
enough, China was going to capture it. I
assure you of that. So Tibet remains
independent hypothetically only if India
is able to safeguard its
sovereignty. That's the only situation
in which China can't capture Tibet
because Tibet had no standing army. They
were all Buddhist monks and all. Hm.
They had a very tiny self-defense force
which was not really um capable of of of
defending the country. So the only
situation the only uh scenario in which
Tibet remains independent is if India
guarantees Tibet's security and safety
and prevents China from capturing it. So
if that scenario is true then Tibet
can't become a US because India will
ensure it doesn't happen. All right.
Manuk Krishna says, "If one becomes an
IAS officer, how can one gain power to
the highest echelons without partaking
in elections and becoming a slave to the
politicians?" I have no idea. Uh, look,
as an IS officer, you have great amount
of power over small people.
So if you're a district collector,
district magistrate or whatever, you
have a tremendous amount of power on all
the
poor all the powerless people, all the
citizens who live in the district. You
have complete power over
them, excuse me. But you have to take
orders from the politicians who are
above you. So as an I is officer you are
always taking orders from
somebody and the higher you rise you
take orders from more and more powerful
politicians. That's how it works. So how
can one gain power to the highest
echelons without partaking in elections
and becoming a slave to the politicians?
Um I'm not quite sure. I'm sure there is
a game that you play and if you play it
well then you can become more powerful
than most politicians. It's possible.
I'm sure. I think to understand how it
works I think you would watch. Yes,
Minister, yes, Prime Minister in which
they've kind of satized how all that
works. You know, the officers, the
bureaucrats are always really the ones
in power and the politicians, they come
and go. It's kind of like that. But I'm
not quite sure how it happens in how it
works in real life. I'm sure it's
possible to a certain extent, possibly,
hypothetically.
Okay. Om. Beher says, "Why did
Yugoslavia disintegrate just 10 years
after Tito's death? Was it due to a
power vacuum or external interference
since the EU formed around the time?
What can India learn from it?" Okay. The
this nation Yugoslavia was a great
experiment. It was kind of a successful
socialist experiment for a change kind
of.
Okay. Why did it disintegrate? It
disintegrated because the USSR collapsed
and disintegrated itself. So the USSR
disintegrates and the USSR was the
guaranteer of security of
Yugoslavia and because that protection
was gone the Americans said now we can
play God now this is the uniolar moment
there's no competition for us there's no
power who can oppose us so let's play
God and let's break up Yugoslavia and
that's what they
did so it's yeah external interference
because of an absence of protective
power over
Yugoslavia which was the
USSR. Um yeah. So what can India learn
from this? India can learn that you know
power is all that matters. Strength is
all that matters. The greatest weakness
in geopolitics geopolitics the greatest
sin in geopolitics is weakness. If you
are weak you're committing a sin. That's
what India can learn.
Karthik Mali says, "Do you think
Hinduism will vanish after a few
centuries as the people don't have much
knowledge about their own religion and
the conversion record is going on and
how Hinduism has shrunk, shrunk, etc.
It's possible if we are not careful. It
could happen. You know, most of us we
don't know much about our own culture,
our own religion compared to what our
grandparents knew. We know very little.
We care very little because the
education system is such that it just
pulls us away. It doesn't teach us
anything about our culture. We don't
learn anything about our ancestors,
about our history, who we are, where we
came from, what our ancestors did, what
fights did, what what struggles they
faced, what their culture is, how much
they fought to safeguard their culture,
the religion and keep it alive. And what
is our religion? What is our culture?
What are the components? Why should
should it be important to us? We are
taught nothing at all. And our parents
generally are too busy working. So they
don't get to teach us anything. So we
are just completely you know dassinated
cut off from our roots and this happens
increasingly generation after generation
and eventually people Indians in most
Indians will have absolutely no
connection to their culture and you see
that in big cities today. So it's
possible that in a few centur maybe in a
few decades Hinduism will essentially
cease to exist. It's possible if we are
not careful but I hope it doesn't
happen. We have survived 10,000 years
more or less. So hopefully we survive
another 10,000
years. So let's be optimistic but let's
be careful is what I would
say. Okay. Sid says do you think Indian
civilization is older than the
Australian civilization? Does Australia
have a civilization? Australia had the
aboriginal people but they never had an
advanced civilization. What's a
civilization? It's an advanced
society that has that is a net exporter
of culture and so many other
characteristics. Australia was cannot be
classified the the the society of the
native people of
Australia. I don't know what it was like
before the invaders came in the the
British came in and destroyed
everything. It doesn't look like they
were very
advanced. So I don't know if it
qualifies to be a civilization. in case
it was a civilization. We don't know
when it it it emerged for the first
time. Um, so I don't know. I don't know.
Our civilization is let's say 10,000
years old perhaps. Okay. Maybe long
maybe older but roughly 10,000 years
old. Uh, did the native Australians also
have something that old? We don't know.
We have found no evidence of that. It's
possible, but we don't know. So, can't
really say.
H
okay Raz says our patent laws are a few
are decades old. Don't you think they
need urgent reform? I think everything
in this country needs urgent reform. I
have not looked at the patent laws so I
don't know how it is like but I'm pretty
sure it's all it all dates back to the
19th century or 18th century. I have no
idea. So I'm sure everything needs
urgent reform. Uh Raji says this is the
last question for today. What's your
opinion on working for the UN? Is it a
good domain to explore jobs for youth
with a few with a few years of corporate
experience? I think working for the UN
is great. You get a lot of
exposure, very little
work, and if you are smart, you can
really have a great life. See, the UN
has a huge budget and it does nothing.
the UN does nothing but it will send you
to different places and it'll give you a
lot of exposure and you will get in
touch with very very famous and
important people and uh if you if you
play the game well you could become very
important person you can get get a lot
of exposure you'll get a good salary as
well these huge budgets they do nothing
with it and most of the budget is spent
on the expenditure and and salaries and
travel and hotel hotels and flights for
their top
brass So, you know, it's it's not a bad
thing to get into. You may become who
knows the next UN Secretary General in
20 30 years if you play your cards
right. So, I'm I'm half joking here, but
I think it's it's a good thing to get
into. You know, you could So, is it a
good domain to explore jobs for youth
with a few years of corporate
experience? I think it's certainly an
interesting thing to explore and it it
it will look good on your CV as well.
So, yeah, go for it. All right, with
that, we are at the end of today's show.
two over 16 minutes plus. So, thank you
so much for all your questions. It was
fun discussing all this
and we'll continue this next weekend.
All right, next weekend I'll take
questions from the comments. Until then,
take care, keep asking questions, keep
raising your standards, and I will see
you very soon in a week's time. Take
care. Bye-bye.